<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Orange Days</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Orange Days</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 21:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Heroes 3 tricks to extract more joy from the game</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/heroes-3-tricks-to-extract-more-joy-from-the-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 21:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/heroes-3-tricks-to-extract-more-joy-from-the-game/</guid>
      <description>I love to play random maps in Heroes 3 (original complete edition with the amazing HD Launcher) against 7 original AI on Impossible difficulty, random choice of town. On top of that, my preferred mode of playing with a friend is Hot Seat. The following text is what keeps me enjoying this game after 20 years of playing and doing the same things over and over again.&#xA;I remember coming across someone else&amp;rsquo;s saved games on our hostel&amp;rsquo;s LAN during my university days.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clone Disk to a Smaller One With Clonezilla</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/clone-disk-to-a-smaller-one-with-clonezilla/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 22:47:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/clone-disk-to-a-smaller-one-with-clonezilla/</guid>
      <description>Clonezilla allows to skip target disk size, and also has an option to create partitions on a new disk proportionally to the old ones.&#xA;In my case there was an HDD with 6 partitions and Windows 10, total size - 500 GB. The last three were C:, D: and the recovery image.&#xA;New SSD was only 240 GB, but as it turned out the partition backup made by Clonezilla took less than 200 GB.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jetpack Compose Navigation Handling of Hilt View Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/jetpack-compose-navigation-handling-of-hilt-view-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 23:33:47 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/jetpack-compose-navigation-handling-of-hilt-view-model/</guid>
      <description>Suppose you want to re-use a ViewModel across two full-screen composables, and for some reason you rely on hiltViewModel() from androidx.hilt:hilt-navigation-compose:1.0.0:&#xA;@Composable fun Comp1(viewModel: SharedViewModel = hiltViewModel()) { ... } @Composable fun Comp2(viewModel: SharedViewModel = hiltViewModel()) { ... } Let&amp;rsquo;s imagine Comp1 navigates to Comp2.&#xA;If you do not pass an explicit handle to existing instance of SharedViewModel to these composables, they will go ahead and create a new one for themselves.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knee Deep in Trouble Merle Travis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/knee-deep-in-trouble-merle-travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 16:51:43 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/knee-deep-in-trouble-merle-travis/</guid>
      <description> (well I&amp;#39;m) kneeeeeeeeeeee deeeeeep in trouble (got the) saaaaaaame thing on my miiiiind (there&amp;#39;s nothing) thrilling (and it&amp;#39;s a) killing meeee -- just keep a kiiilling tiiiiime (it&amp;#39;s agi)tating, wading -- it&amp;#39;s aggravating (and I&amp;#39;m) left nothing come (to) looooung (I&amp;#39;ll be) kneeeeeeeeee eeeeeee deeeeep in trouble -- till my baby comes home (tururu) pa tu bu bruuuu bu pa pu (I&amp;#39;ve had the) mumps, the bumps, (and) all kinda trumps (I&amp;#39;ve had the) groove and the hoop (in) call (I&amp;#39;ve had the) aches, the shakes, -- and everythang it takes --(to) really bump the good man off (but have my) troubles double --looodi, what a muddle --everythang&amp;#39;s getting to beeeeeeeee -- aaaaammm standing knee deep in trouble --since my honey let me beeeee (well amm) kneeeeeee eeeeeee deeeep in trouble (got the) same thing on my maaaaaind (there&amp;#39;s nothing) thrilling (and it&amp;#39;s a) killing me --(to) just keep the killing taaaaaaaaim (it&amp;#39;s agi)tating, wading, -- it&amp;#39;s aggravating (and I&amp;#39;m) left nothing come(to) loooooong (I&amp;#39;ll be) kneeeeeeee eeeeeeee deeeep in trouble -- till my baby comes hoououo-ome -- till my baby comes home comon home, baby -- till my baby comes hooooouume taaaaa aaaa puruppuumm (mm)datt&amp;#39;tee du weeeeee </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Android Xml Layouts With Jetpack Compose</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/using-android-xml-layouts-with-jetpack-compose/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 16:51:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/using-android-xml-layouts-with-jetpack-compose/</guid>
      <description>The documentation suggests to use AndroidViewBinding API for the task.&#xA;I intended to learn Compose in my project, but also wanted a LineChart from MPAndroidChart library.&#xA;Here is what I did. In the fragment:&#xA;override fun onCreateView( inflater: LayoutInflater, container: ViewGroup?, savedInstanceState: Bundle? ): View? { val lineChart = FragmentChartBinding.inflate(inflater) return ComposeView(requireContext()).apply { setContent { SetContent(viewModel, findNavController(), lineChart) } } } And in the composable:&#xA;@Composable fun setChart( state: State&amp;lt;List&amp;lt;BodyMeasurement.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strapi Gatsby Blog</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/strapi-gatsby-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 13:13:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/strapi-gatsby-blog/</guid>
      <description>Here is the path I took to host my personal site with Strapi + Gatsby setup.&#xA;I had only one previous experience hosting a personal website, that was self hosting with Ghost platform version 3. It was a good one with a very intuitive article creation and editing process.&#xA;I decided to try something else, and then learned there are headless CMS solutions which may work with any static site generator.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit Network Bandwidth for a Virtual Machine on Linux</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/limit-network-bandwidth-for-a-virtual-machine-on-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 11:52:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/limit-network-bandwidth-for-a-virtual-machine-on-linux/</guid>
      <description>Something very useful - find the name of the virtual NIC on the host, and run a magical tc command:&#xA;# ip l | grep vnet 47: vnet1: &amp;lt;BROADCAST,MULTICAST,UP,LOWER_UP&amp;gt; mtu 1500 qdisc htb master virbr0 state UNKNOWN mode DEFAULT group default qlen 1000 # tc class change dev vnet1 classid 1:1 root htb rate 100Mbit Here is an example of me using it to choke Steam:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qemu Passthrough for Sm2262 Sm2263 Based Ssd</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/qemu-passthrough-for-sm2262-sm2263-based-ssd/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 11:38:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/qemu-passthrough-for-sm2262-sm2263-based-ssd/</guid>
      <description>I have an NVMe device that I use to passthrough to a virtual machine on Linux. It has some internal issue, a workaround that worked for me so far was described here:&#xA;&amp;lt;hostdev mode=&amp;#34;subsystem&amp;#34; type=&amp;#34;pci&amp;#34; managed=&amp;#34;yes&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;source&amp;gt; &amp;lt;address domain=&amp;#34;0x0000&amp;#34; bus=&amp;#34;0x6f&amp;#34; slot=&amp;#34;0x00&amp;#34; function=&amp;#34;0x0&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/source&amp;gt; &amp;lt;boot order=&amp;#34;1&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;alias name=&amp;#34;ua-sm2262&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;address type=&amp;#34;pci&amp;#34; domain=&amp;#34;0x0000&amp;#34; bus=&amp;#34;0x00&amp;#34; slot=&amp;#34;0x07&amp;#34; function=&amp;#34;0x0&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/hostdev&amp;gt; &amp;lt;qemu:commandline&amp;gt; &amp;lt;qemu:arg value=&amp;#34;-set&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;qemu:arg value=&amp;#34;device.ua-sm2262.x-msix-relocation=bar2&amp;#34;/&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/qemu:commandline&amp;gt; Since some release of qemu it seems to no longer work and give an error message like this:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fingerstyle Tabs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/fingerstyle-tabs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 00:22:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/fingerstyle-tabs/</guid>
      <description>I learnt how to play things on the guitar mostly because of great tabs published at https://frettedinstrumentsnyc.com. For me this was the only way to stay learning, because just doing &amp;ldquo;exercises&amp;rdquo; makes no sense to my brain as there is no music produced that is remotely pleasurable to hear.&#xA;With the tabs you instead can already mimic your favorite tunes - all that is required is some technical work to make your fingers accustomed to the changes in chord shapes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Encrypting Existing Linux Installation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/encrypting-existing-linux-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 23:38:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/encrypting-existing-linux-installation/</guid>
      <description>I have an Arch (Gnome) on one physical disk and Ubuntu on another. At some point I decided to encrypt the Ubuntu installation. Ubuntu was just sitting on a simple /dev/nvme1n1p1 partition. I added a separate boot /dev/nvme1n1p2 device to keep grub on, and it had its benefits too. Main bootloader lives on the Arch disk.&#xA;I followed the steps on Arch wiki, but during the boot there was no prompt to put password for decryption.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
